# TEMWEKA SCOLASTICA CHIRWA

#### **Data Scientist**

@ temweka.chirwa@gmail.com

**J** +27 83 790 6641

Johannesburg, South Africa

in temweka-chirwa/

# **SUMMARY**

I am a data scientist with 4+ years of experience working in the data science space, with applications relating to ecological and medical research. My work mainly focused on machine learning and artificial intelligence applications in medical diagnostics. Before I transitioned into data science, I worked as a civil engineer interested in sustainable and environmental engineering. My research interests include machine learning, computer vision and AI applications in different fields such as medical diagnostics and climate change.

# **EXPERIENCE**

# Machine Learning Bootcamp Learning Assistant GetSmarter, a 2U, Inc. brand

November 2023 - Ongoing

Remote, Part-time

Offering remote assistance to students in the Machine Learning and Artificial Intelligence Bootcamp Programmes, my role includes:

- Mentorship and guidance via Zoom session.
- Written and video support to students via Slack and Zoom.
- · Grading of assignments and homework.

# Data Science Research Assistant Perinatal HIV Research Unit (PHRU)

☐ March 2021 - November 2023 Soweto, Johannesburg

Helping the organisation utilise machine learning on their vast medical data to create innovative diagnostic tools. My roles and duties included:

- Developing ML tools for disease detection in low-resource set-
- Creating patient monitoring and visualization tools for various clinical projects
- Proposal Writing and reviewing of abstracts
- Bi-weekly presentations and progress updates with collaborators.
- Presenting work at conferences, namely, Africomp 2022, and RED-Cap Africa Day (2022 & 2023)

# Junior Civil Engineer

### **Zitholele Consulting**

February 2017 - January 2019

Midrand, Johannesburg

Rising from intern to junior civil engineer, I was involved in various projects with roles that included:

- Conducting site supervision, works and payment verification on a water and sanitation provision project to rural schools in Limpopo.
- Managing logistical planning and environmental inspection on a derelict mines rehabilitation project.

# **EDUCATION**

#### M.Sc. in Data Science

#### The University of Cape Town

**1** 2019 - 2021

Thesis title: The detection and isolation of prey capture events in the animal-borne video

B.Sc. in Civil Engineering

The University of Witwatersrand

**2013 - 2016** 

# TECHNICAL SKILLS



# **VOLUNTEER WORK**

#### **Data Scientist**

#### **FemAnalytica**

📋 2023 - Present

Remote

Part of a team that aims to use our data science expertise to develop innovative databased solutions for social good

### Python Programming Teacher LadyCode SA

**1** 2021 - 2023

Johannesburg

Taught Python to Grade 10 and 11 students from underprivileged schools in Alexandra Township.

### REFEREES

#### **Dr Kennedy Otwombe**

@ Statistician - Perinatal HIV Research Unit

otwombek@phru.co.za

**(**+27) 11 989 9807

#### Dr Ian Durbach

@ Adjunct Associate Professor - School of Statistical Sciences, The University of Cape

✓ indurbach@gmail.com